<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000623, ex. 009</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346192</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346192.P346192.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1'">You stand/serve according to(?) the command of An</l>
        <l n="2'">My lady, the mountain bows towards/on behalf of your shout</l>
        <l n="3'">...</l>
        <l n="4'">Along with the aura, radiance, and the southern stormwind(?), you have brought(?) for yourself(?) the furious(?) stupor of the people to the fore</l>
        <l n="5'">You have taken the (most) furious of the cosmic powers for yourself</l>
        <l n="6'">The “threshold of mourning” has opened for you</l>
        <l n="7'">... goes on the street of the temple(?) of greatest lamentation/great lamentations (i.e., the netherworld?) for you</l>
        <l n="8'">From the front of battle things (that are shot, flung?) are removed for you (i.e., diverted?)</l>
        <l n="9'">My lady, (in/with) your own power “flints&quot;(? i.e., sparks?) consume(!?)</l>
        <l n="10'">You thrash like a thrashing storm</l>
        <l n="11'">(You) shout together with the shouting storm</l>
        <l n="12'">(You) scream along with Iškur</l>
        <l n="13'">You are to become exhausted together with the destructive winds</l>
        <l n="14'">(But) inexhaustiveness is worn (on) your feet (as footwear)</l>
        <l n="15'">... performs a lament with the balag drum of weeping</l>
        <l n="16'">My lady, the Anuna, the Anuna, the great gods</l>
        <l n="17'">Like flying bats, they have been driven into(!?) the ruin mound/cracks(?) because of you</l>
        <l n="18'">They are not to stand(?) (at) your furious face</l>
        <l n="19'">Not one (of them) can confront your furious forehead</l>
        <l n="20'">Who will cool your angry heart?</l>
        <l n="21'">The cooling(!?) of your malevolent heart is a supreme(ly challenging undertaking)</l>
        <l n="22'">Lady, (your) liver is good, (your) heart rejoices</l>
        <l n="23'">(But your) anger does not cool, eldest child of Nanna</l>
        <l n="24'">Lady who surpasses the land/mountain/netherworld(?), who has deprived you?</l>
        <l n="25'">The mountain range extends with you in your place, (it is) the taboo of (reserved for) Ezina (the grain goddess)</l>
        <l n="26'">Fire was imposed on its gate</l>
        <l n="27'">Blood is poured into its rivers for you and therefore the people cannot drink</l>
        <l n="28'">Its army plunders(?) itself for you</l>
        <l n="29'">The formations split themselves apart for you</l>
        <l n="30'">Its able-bodied young men serve you by themselves(?)</l>
        <l n="31'">A northern storm(?) has filled its cities and playgrounds(?)</l>
        <l n="32'">Its perfect young men stood as captives(?)</l>
        <l n="33'">The city that has not (compelled its people) to say “the land/mountain is for you”</l>
        <l n="34'">Nor has (its people) said “your father (...)”</l>
        <l n="1'">(I?) approached the shade, but it was covered by (lit. along with) a southern storm(?)</l>
        <l n="2'">My “honey mouth” was ...</l>
        <l n="3'">My “thing that gladdened the liver” was turned back with the dust(?)</l>
        <l n="4'">My fate, (involving?) Suen and lugalane</l>
        <l n="5'">Speak to An, so that he undoes it for me</l>
        <l n="6'">Now, she will speak to An, he will have released(!?) me</l>
        <l n="7'">The woman will take away the fate (involving?) lugalane</l>
        <l n="8'">Mountain and flood alike lie/crouch at her feet</l>
        <l n="9'">That woman is also supreme, she can besiege(!?) the city</l>
        <l n="10'">Stand/serve, so that she is cooled in her heart to/for me</l>
        <l n="11'">I am Enheduana, and I shall perform an arazu prayer for you</l>
        <l n="12'">...</l>
        <l n="13'">I(!) shall release my tears like sweet beer for holy Inanna, I shall say to you “(give?) your legal decision”</l>
        <l n="14'">I/you(?) shall not exhaust/bother Dilimbabbar(?)</l>
        <l n="15'">Within(?) the cleansing rites of holy An, everything of his(?) is changed</l>
        <l n="16'">And thus (Lugalane) has removed the Eanna temple from An</l>
        <l n="17'">He did not fear An, the greatest one</l>
        <l n="18'">He did not solidify(!?) the charm of that temple did not satisfy, he did not fulfill its allure</l>
        <l n="19'">He has turned that temple into an evil (temple)</l>
        <l n="20'">When(?) he entered ..., he drew his envy near(?)</l>
        <l n="21'">May my “true wild cow&quot;(?) chase that man away, may you seize that man</l>
        <l n="22'">In the place of life giving force/encouragement, what(!?) am I? (i.e., why am I here making this prayer?)</l>
        <l n="23'">The rebel land, because of hatred of your Nanna/in the manner of (one) hated by your Nanna(?), may An hand it over</l>
        <l n="24'">May An tear apart its city</l>
        <l n="25'">May Enlil curse it</l>
        <l n="26'">His mother shall not calm down its weeping child/citizen</l>
        <l n="27'">Lady whose lament is under way(?)</l>
        <l n="28'">May your boat of lamentation be abandoned in a strange place</l>
        <l n="29'">I am to “die” because of my holy song</l>
        <l n="30'">(But) as for me, my Nanna has not inquired after me</l>
        <l n="31'">He has caused my utter destruction(?) in a “place of violence”</l>
        <l n="32'">Dilimbabbar has not undertaken my case</l>
        <l n="33'">(If) he did, what is it to me? (If) he did not, what is it to me?</l>
        <l n="34'">After/when(?) triumphing, he (Lugalane) drove me out from the temple</l>
        <l n="35'">Like a swallow, he made me fly away from the window</l>
        <l n="1">You make (me) go(!?) in the brambles of the mountain</l>
        <l n="2">He removed the true crown of the en priestess from (my head)</l>
        <l n="3">He gave a knife and dagger to me and said to me “it is suitable for you”</l>
        <l n="4">Most precious lady, loved by An</l>
        <l n="5">May (your) holy heart, which is supreme, be restored to its place for me</l>
        <l n="6">Beloved spouse of (Ama)'ušumgalana (Dumuzi)</l>
        <l n="7">You are the great queen of the horizon and zenith (i.e., the whole of heaven)</l>
        <l n="8">The Anuna have submitted to you</l>
        <l n="9">How (you) have been superior to the Anuna, the great gods!</l>
        <l n="10">Since birth you have been the younger sister (of Utu)</l>
        <l n="11">The Anuna kiss the ground with their lips for you</l>
        <l n="12">My case has not been finalized, (but the threat of) a hostile decision, apart from my case(?), prowls around(?) in my face</l>
        <l n="13">He (Lugalane) has not defiled the flowered bed</l>
        <l n="14">The uttered word of Ningal has not been released to him</l>
        <l n="15">I am the pure/bright en priestess of Nanna</l>
        <l n="16">My lady beloved by An, may your heart be cooled to me</l>
        <l n="17">May it be known, may it be known, what has not been said (of) Nanna('s), (but) what has been said of you</l>
        <l n="18">Which is: “may your being supreme like heaven be known”</l>
        <l n="19">Which is “may your being broad like the earth be known”</l>
        <l n="20">Which is “may your red face be known”</l>
        <l n="21">Which is “may your brown face be known”</l>
        <l n="22">Which is “may your furiously raised eye be known”</l>
        <l n="23">Which is “may your corpse-eating like a dog be known”</l>
        <l n="24">Which is “may your head bashing be known”</l>
        <l n="25">Which is “may your destruction of the rebel country be known”</l>
        <l n="26">Which is “may your being mighty(?) and (dis)obedient(?) be known”</l>
        <l n="27">Which is “may your shouting at the foreign land/mountain be known”</l>
        <l n="28">(This is) what has not been said (of) Nanna('s), (but) what has been said of you</l>
        <l n="29">My lady, (you did these things?) the greatest(?), you are supreme</l>
        <l n="30">My lady beloved of An, I shall speak of(?) your anger(?)</l>
        <l n="31">The charcoal has been piled up, the cleansing rites have been set in order</l>
        <l n="32">The “holy tavern” is opened for you/there for you, (but) your heart shall cool(?) for me</l>
        <l n="33">After it (the matter) filled up and became too much, lady and queen, (as has) been spoken to you(?)</l>
        <l n="34">That which was said to you in the nighttime</l>
        <l n="35">The lamentation priest shall repeat at(?) midday for you</l>
        <l n="36">Because of your captured spouse, because of your captured child</l>
        <l n="1">Inanna, praise</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
