<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000793, ex. 005</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346130</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346130.P346130.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1'">My fish, so that the one(s) who sleep (there) are not(!?) woken up</l>
        <l n="2'">So that the one(s) who dwell (there) do not(!?) quarrel</l>
        <l n="3'">Enter for me, my beloved child</l>
        <l n="4'">Enter for me, my beautiful child</l>
        <l n="5'">Like a brackish waterway, do not discover the irrigation ditch(?)</l>
        <l n="6'">Like river silt, do not learn how to rise (i.e., be excavated(?))</l>
        <l n="7'">Like flowing water, do not diminish(!?) your recumbency(?)</l>
        <l n="8'">Do not bring moonlight into the(?) house when you lie down(?)</l>
        <l n="9'">May you also not be able to go away from(?) me, (set) your face to where I am</l>
        <l n="10'">May you also not be able to go (away) like a dog sniffing the ground, (set) your face to where I am</l>
        <l n="11'">May you also not be able to go away like a ... towards your fodder, (set) your face to where I am</l>
        <l n="12'">In your manner of going like a prostitute towards the tavern</l>
        <l n="13'">May you not be able to go away from(?) me, (set) your face to where I am</l>
        <l n="14'">In your manner of entering like a bull into the cattlepen</l>
        <l n="15'">My fish, may Dilimbabbar rejoice with you</l>
        <l n="16'">In your manner of entering like a sheep into the sheepfold</l>
        <l n="17'">My fish, may Dumuzi, the shepherd, rejoice with you</l>
        <l n="1'">My fish, my ... fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="2'">...</l>
        <l n="3'">My fish, my eštub carp, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="4'">A black boat pole cast into the field</l>
        <l n="6'">Nursemaid giving birth(?), taking away(?) dough (from) the riverbank</l>
        <l n="7'">My fish, my gubi eel, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="8'">(Possessing) a spiked tail, a spiked dorsal fin(?), plundering from the u land(?)</l>
        <l n="9'">My fish, my great ubi fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="10'">A fish which within its lips is like a crying child</l>
        <l n="11'">My fish, my thin? ubi fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="12'">(Its) head is a hoe, (its) teeth are a comb</l>
        <l n="13'">Its skeleton is the top of a conifer tree</l>
        <l n="14'">Its air bladder(!?) is the waterskin of Dumuzi</l>
        <l n="15'">Its thin tail is the whip of (i.e., that threatens?) fishermen</l>
        <l n="16'">(Its) skin is dehaired (i.e., scaled?) and does not need to be worked by hand(?)</l>
        <l n="17'">My fish, my mur fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="18'">The fins (of) that fish turned back roiled water (i.e., it leaves a wake)</l>
        <l n="19'">My fish, my kin fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="1">(Its) head is millstone (with) its pounding stone, (with the) paws and head of a dog(?)</l>
        <l n="2">Its shoulder is to smite/it is to make its shoulder leap(?), its back(?) is to plant a (mooring) post (i.e., it is difficult to remove from the water?)</l>
        <l n="3">My fish, my pešgid fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="4">The cry of its intestines(?), the base of its neck (are ...?)</l>
        <l n="5">My fish, my peš fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="6">... placing/preparing ..., a fish who has discovered(?) how to escape a “reed fence” (i.e., fish trap?)</l>
        <l n="7">A fish (to whom?) fighting is taboo(?)</l>
        <l n="8">My fish, my absuhur carp, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="9">The fish who sets up(?) derision/derides (like a clown?), placing bile in(?) its jaw</l>
        <l n="10">My fish, my agargara fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="11">My child of the merchant, sprinkling(?) dairy products(?)</l>
        <l n="12">My fish, my kamar fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="13">The child of the Martu nomads, ... by(?) back/from the outside(?)</l>
        <l n="14">My fish, my nunbarhuš fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="15">A fish that does not eat edible plants(?), ... water ...</l>
        <l n="16">My fish, my azaggur fish, may it too enter with you</l>
        <l n="17">(Possessing) heavy skin(?), ...</l>
        <l n="18">My fish, my “snake” fish(?) ...</l>
        <l n="19">...</l>
        <l n="1">The one shouting(?) malevolently in the marshes of the river</l>
        <l n="2">My fish, my akanni bird would bind you to (its) claws</l>
        <l n="3">When(?) the sabar net is stretched out in the water(?), prowling around(?) the sapar net</l>
        <l n="4">My fish, my uburri bird would bind you to (its) claws</l>
        <l n="5">(Possessing) feet that raise, laughing</l>
        <l n="6">Darting from the shallows</l>
        <l n="7">My fish, my kišibar bird would bind you to (its) claws</l>
        <l n="8">Not adorning ...</l>
        <l n="9">... of a bird, ... of a fish</l>
        <l n="10">My fish, my kib bird would bind you to (its) claws</l>
        <l n="11">A quadruped that dives and dwells in/passes through(?) the marshes</l>
        <l n="12">My fish, my kuda animal (otter?) would bind you to (its) paw</l>
        <l n="13">They(?) will not bind you to (their) claws/front paws, they will not bind you to (their) claws/rear paws</l>
        <l n="14">My fish, time elapses, come before me</l>
        <l n="15">Time elapses, come before me</l>
        <l n="16">May Nanše?, the lady of the fisherman, rejoice for you</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
