<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000481, ex. 016</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346171</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346171.P346171.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">I am one (whose) supplication/prayers make Ninlil rejoice</l>
        <l n="2">I am the unceasing one serving Nuska</l>
        <l n="3">I am one whose hand is oriented(?) towards the Ki'ur</l>
        <l n="4">I am the fitting one for carrying things and running(?)</l>
        <l n="5">I am one constantly hurrying (but) whose knees do not tire</l>
        <l n="6">I am the bringer of the nesag offering who does not allow light to pass through(?) the Ebabbar temple</l>
        <l n="7">I am the one who chases(?) abundance towards/on behalf of Nippur</l>
        <l n="8">In Keš I am the one serving as(?) its išib priest</l>
        <l n="9">On behalf of Urim I am the first rate butter and cream</l>
        <l n="10">On behalf of Eridu I am its unceasing one</l>
        <l n="11">On behalf of the site of Unug I am the great nindaba offerings</l>
        <l n="12">I am the one given life by the Ekur temple(?)</l>
        <l n="13">I am the one who wishes for vitality on behalf of his city</l>
        <l n="14">I am lipit-Ištar, the shepherd of the lands</l>
        <l n="15">I am the king, a wave thrashing towards battle</l>
        <l n="16">I am one who does not loosen the knots of the bindings of youthfulness</l>
        <l n="17">I am the one sharpening the giri'ura knife</l>
        <l n="18">In battle I am the one flashing like lightning</l>
        <l n="1">I am one who establishes the foundation and destroys among the troops</l>
        <l n="2">I am the sagkal stone(?), the stone that ...(?)</l>
        <l n="3">I am a shield, the watcher of the army</l>
        <l n="4">I am the bright-faced hero who solidifies the troop formation</l>
        <l n="5">I am lipit-Ištar, the son of Enlil</l>
        <l n="6">I am a waterskin (of) cold water, the life of the young man/worker</l>
        <l n="7">I am the one who watches the campaign, the (protective) shade of the troops</l>
        <l n="8">I am a king that when he sits, he goes on(!?) the dais</l>
        <l n="9">I put important thoughts to words(?)</l>
        <l n="10">I am one (who possesses) profound intellect and counsel(!?), seeking the (correct) way</l>
        <l n="11">I am one who does not hurry(!?) anything, ...</l>
        <l n="12">I am one (who possesses) profound thought and broad understanding</l>
        <l n="13">&quot;Long-tablet&quot; of Ningešzida-...</l>
        <l n="14">month o&quot;NENEgar,&quot; 13th day,</l>
        <l n="15">year &quot;Isin ...&quot;.</l>
        <l n="1">... 30 (lines ...)</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
