<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000581, ex. 003</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346260</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346260.P346260.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1-3">After you speak to Enlilmassu, (the provider of) sweet words and good advice, the (possessor of) a “honey mouth, who ... speech</l>
        <l n="4-5.a">To the son who serves his god, one who his father and mother</l>
        <l n="5b">fears, after you repeat,</l>
        <l n="6-7">My alad spirit, my lamma spirit, my valued (personal) god (Akkadian, the one of the side(?)), with good features and stature</l>
        <l n="8-9.a">Embodiment of the scribal art, hero of the šatam officials,</l>
        <l n="9.b">ornament of the palace. Who restores commands to their place</l>
        <l n="10-11">Who sweetens the heart of the king, after you (say) a third time to him</l>
        <l n="1-3">Lugalnesage, the nu'eš priest of Enlil, the jester of the king</l>
        <l n="4-6">Son of Enlilalsag, master (scribe) of Nibru, your father, it is (him who) speaks (thusly)</l>
        <l n="7">When I was abandoned, (I) was “cut down&quot;(?)</l>
        <l n="8-9">My heart fell, I am one whose (interest in) eating and drinking diminishes</l>
        <l n="10-11">Your destiny? consumed me, your laughter! (Akkadian: complaint?) silenced me(?)</l>
        <l n="12">Your greatness (i.e., arrogance) (Akkadian your lot(?)) has twisted(?) me</l>
        <l n="13">(Your) slander/complaining(?) and (feigned) compassion(!?) has killed me</l>
        <l n="14">(For the time being) I have abandoned (Akkadian cut off) my attentiveness (to you)</l>
        <l n="15">When(?) I was afraid, my heart filled with blood and pus</l>
        <l n="16">(I) have been distressed to inquire after (you)</l>
        <l n="17">(But) because(?) ... has not yet ... it into the “place of fate&quot;(?)</l>
        <l n="1">By the command of Enlil, may I(?) see your face (again).</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
