<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000339, ex. 021</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346100</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346100.P346100.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">I want to bring a great bull against its supreme power(?)</l>
        <l n="2">I want to bring a small bull against its small power(?)</l>
        <l n="3">I want to run(?) there, I want to chase the holy skipping rope there</l>
        <l n="4">In the mountain I want to continually go(?) to(?) battle, I want to chase the battle(?)</l>
        <l n="5">I shall set the arrow that is (in) my quiver(?) straight</l>
        <l n="6">I want to twist slingstones (together) like a heavy rope</l>
        <l n="7">I want to polish the spear</l>
        <l n="8">I(!?) want to have the throwstick and shield(!?) set in order</l>
        <l n="9">I want to strike its adjoining forests with fire</l>
        <l n="10">I want to ... the hazin axe against its evildoers</l>
        <l n="11">I want to station Gibil the purifier to work in its standing water</l>
        <l n="12">I want to submerge/make distant(?) its aura among(?) the mountain range of Aratta, which no hand can approach</l>
        <l n="13">Like a city cursed by An, it shall not return it to its place, to its place!</l>
        <l n="1">Like one frowned at by Enlil, it shall not raise its neck there(?)</l>
        <l n="2">The mountain should wish for/observe(?) my way</l>
        <l n="3">Ebih should praise me, Ebih should extol me</l>
        <l n="4">An, the king of the gods, was replying</l>
        <l n="5">My child, you(?) have desired the mountain, (but) what will its midst accomplish(?)</l>
        <l n="6">You are the lady, the one who has desired the mountain, (but) what will (its) midst accomplish(?)</l>
        <l n="7">You are Inanna, the one who has desired the mountain, (but) what will (its) midst accomplish(?)</l>
        <l n="8">(You are the one) who has desired the mountain range of Ebih, (but) what will (its) midst accomplish(?)</l>
        <l n="9">The abode/station of the gods is imposed with a furious aura</l>
        <l n="10">And thus(?) a radiance is released upon the holy dwelling of the Anuna</l>
        <l n="11">The red/furious aura of the mountain range is imposed upon the lands</l>
        <l n="12">Its height is “of heaven&quot;(?), its horn(?) brought out(?) ...</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
