<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000364, ex. 048</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346142</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346142.P346142.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">The ibbaru harness, there was fifty mina within it, ... on his hips</l>
        <l n="2">He tied on the fifty (mina)</l>
        <l n="3.a">of his hazin axe, (the weapon of) his campaign,</l>
        <l n="3.b">which weighed 7 talents and 7 mina, he took hold</l>
        <l n="4">At the base (of the halub tree) he smote the snake that was immune to incantations</l>
        <l n="5">In its branches, the Anzu bird took its chick and dragged it away(?) to the mountain range</l>
        <l n="6.a">The demon maidens(?) of the empty wind who had built(?) a house in its middle(!?</l>
        <l n="6.b">fled to the wasteland</l>
        <l n="7">He struck the tree at its trunk and cut its branches</l>
        <l n="8.a">The citizens of his city who had come to him</l>
        <l n="8.b">made it submit/gathered (the branches)(?)</l>
        <l n="9">They gave it to his sister, holy Inanna, as her throne</l>
        <l n="10">They gave it to her as her bed</l>
        <l n="11">He(!?) took(?) the base of the tree for his ball/How the base of the tree was taken for his ball!(?)</l>
        <l n="1">He(!?) took(?) the branches of the tree for his mallet</l>
        <l n="2">The one who always played ball(?) brings out the ball in the smoothed(!?) street</l>
        <l n="3-4">The one who always boasted about himself(?) brings out the ball in the smoothed(!?) street; the young men(?) of his city who always played ball(?)</l>
        <l n="5">(Because of?) him, (the one by whom?) the force of widow's children was ridden(?)</l>
        <l n="6">They lamented (with the phrase) “oh, my neck, oh, my hips(?)!”</l>
        <l n="7">Those who had a mother, she was bringing food for her son</l>
        <l n="8">Those who had a sister, she was pouring(?) water for her brother</l>
        <l n="9">Away from/by means of(?) the accusation of the widows</l>
        <l n="10">And the cries to Utu of the young maidens</l>
        <l n="11">He dropped(?) his ball and my(!) mallet into the bottom of the netherworld</l>
        <l n="12">He brought his hand (up to it), and could not touch it</l>
        <l n="13">He brought his foot (up to it), and could not touch it</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
