<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>UET 6, 0161 + 0164 + 0619</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346246</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346246.P346246.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1'">When you are to cross the street, do not look around. If you are humble</l>
        <l n="2'">And (you) fear your overseer</l>
        <l n="3'">Your overseer will love you</l>
        <l n="4'">If the objective is to be achieved, when you speak to(?) your companion</l>
        <l n="5'">Do not turn behind for him</l>
        <l n="6'">Do not denigrate your colleagues</l>
        <l n="7'">If (you?) are going because the day is about to arrive(?)</l>
        <l n="8'">How long shall I stay?</l>
        <l n="9'">I know(?)--(until) my master has left</l>
        <l n="2'">Because of what I am, I did not send (you?) as one charged with the task(?) to carry reeds (from) the reed bed</l>
        <l n="3'">The old/dead reeds which (even) the tiny and little (children) carry</l>
        <l n="4'">Because of what you are, you have not carried them</l>
        <l n="5'">In no way/at no time(?) have I said “Stand(?) at the rear of an ox”</l>
        <l n="6'">Regarding my ox, I did not send (you?) as one charged with the task(?) to follow it</l>
        <l n="7'">Regarding my field, I did not send (you?) as one charged with the task(?) to hoe it</l>
        <l n="8'">Regarding my field, I did not send (you?) as one charged with the task(?) to sow/cultivate it</l>
        <l n="9'">I did not send (you?) as a messenger (charged with a task?) to do a task(?) (or?) to hoe</l>
        <l n="10'">Come! After you do the work, eat food</l>
        <l n="11'">Because of who I am, (I) have not spoken to you (about this)</l>
        <l n="12'">Because of who you are, you have not done the task (but) you did eat the food(?)</l>
        <l n="13'">When a person like you does(?) a task</l>
        <l n="14'">His father and mother will eat food</l>
        <l n="15'">If you observe the ... of my colleagues</l>
        <l n="16'">Like (i.e., each one of?) them, ten gur of barley apiece</l>
        <l n="17'">They place(?) at the head (i.e., provide)</l>
        <l n="18'">(Even) the tiny ones, the “slave of their(!?) fathers,” ten gur of barley apiece they place(?) at the head (i.e., provide)</l>
        <l n="19'">The one(s) who increase (the amount of) grain (for) their fathers</l>
        <l n="1">They have given/brought(?) barley, oil/butter, and sheep wool(?)</l>
        <l n="2">As a man, I(!) exceed you</l>
        <l n="3">You are not a man like (each one of) them</l>
        <l n="4">My son, their fathers</l>
        <l n="5">Dispatched their children/juniors charged with a task(?)</l>
        <l n="6">My(!?) inferior(?), like them</l>
        <l n="7">They do not compare with you in (the performance of) assigned tasks(?)</l>
        <l n="8">Excessive (is) my exertion for you</l>
        <l n="9">Who is it that has exerted himself for his son more that I?</l>
        <l n="10">My words which I recite to you (are as follows?)</l>
        <l n="11">It has not (previously been the case?)! Have fear! It has not (previously been the case?)! Have shame!</l>
        <l n="12">Your companion, with whom you are standing in the same yoke</l>
        <l n="13">... your comrade, your friend, you do not observe them</l>
        <l n="14">Why do you not assimilate with them?</l>
        <l n="15">It has not (previously been the case?)! (Now) assimilate with (your) “big brothers”</l>
        <l n="16">It has not (previously been the case?)! (Now) assimilate with (your) “little brothers”</l>
        <l n="17">From the (ranks of) skilled humanity that resides in the land(?)</l>
        <l n="18">Come!(!?) Enki (himself) has discovered that(?) nothing that has a name (among them)</l>
        <l n="19">Is as painstaking as the assigned task(?) of the place of(?) scribal art</l>
        <l n="20">Nothing that could be named(?), except for the art of the musician</l>
        <l n="21">Like the shores of the sea, where one shore is separated far away from the other</l>
        <l n="22">Thus the content of the art of the musician is esoteric</l>
        <l n="1">You can be idle(?) for eternity</l>
        <l n="2">Greatly your “that which is released” has been enlarged(?)</l>
        <l n="3">Because your ... reputation has not been smitten(?)</l>
        <l n="4">Because (your?) reputation has not been beaten into the dust(?)</l>
        <l n="5">Because of what has been destroyed(?) I will recite to you (the following(?)) for my benefit(?)</l>
        <l n="6">...</l>
        <l n="7">What now to do?(!?)</l>
        <l n="8">That which I did was not ...</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
