<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000764, ex. 006</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346126</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346126.P346126.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">A 2nd time the bird insulted the fish</l>
        <l n="2">The fish, possessed of anger, trusting in the heroic might of the deep water(?)</l>
        <l n="3">Like a heavy rain cloud it set itself on the ground, it stood in an adamin contest</l>
        <l n="4">Whatever insults the bird had struck it with, in did not ponder</l>
        <l n="5">It was able to(?) submit furious(ly)(?), it was speaking freely/humbly(?)</l>
        <l n="6">A 2(diš)nd time fish was answering the bird</l>
        <l n="7">(Possessor of) trimmed limbs, crippled(?) feet, a ... mouth/beak, and a thinned out/flattened(?) tongue</l>
        <l n="8">By means of ignorance you have been able to sneer/shout/chew(?), (but) you yourself have not contemplated(?)</l>
        <l n="9">Eating way too much, ..., filling the courtyard with feces</l>
        <l n="10">The young courtyard sweeper who is sweeping in the temple is braiding(?) a rope for you</l>
        <l n="11">The cook, the brewer, and the gatekeeper who reside in the temple are distressed with (you)</l>
        <l n="12">Bird, (you are one who) my greatness does not tread behind, (you are one who) does not inquire after me</l>
        <l n="13">You cannot know (either) my weakness(?) or my strength, (you) have conversed in an inflammatory manner(?)</l>
        <l n="1">You have not sought the site of my deeds, (now) humble yourself excessively!</l>
        <l n="2">Your word has brought “release,” you have not taken counsel with yourself</l>
        <l n="3">I, the fish, am the one who piles up(?) the abundance of the pure shrine/sea(?) together</l>
        <l n="4">At(?) The supreme mound(?), I am the one who brings/goes/stands among(?) the great nindaba offerings of the gods proudly</l>
        <l n="5">Like (the grain goddess) Ašnan (I) am here as the sustenance of the land, I am her helper</l>
        <l n="6">The people have listened to me, they have looked to me</l>
        <l n="7">The land(?) rejoices with me as if (it was) a festival, my inquirer is there(?)</l>
        <l n="8">Bird, what is your great thing that (you) accomplished? I will make you know your (over) exuberance</l>
        <l n="9">I want to give (back into) your hand your arrogance and false speech</l>
        <l n="10">At that time the fish was setting plans in place against the bird</l>
        <l n="11">Silently and deceptively(?) it went on its “arms”</l>
        <l n="12">When the bird got up from its nest in order to bring (back) food for its chick</l>
        <l n="13">The fish sought? the place silent(ly) “on its arms”</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
