<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000761, ex. 038</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346118</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346118.P346118.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">On the mountain range (spanning) both heaven and earth</l>
        <l n="2">When An fathered the Anuna gods</l>
        <l n="3">Because no one had been able to give birth to or create Ašnan (yet)</l>
        <l n="4">Because the flax of (the weaving goddess) Uttu had not been created along with them</l>
        <l n="5">Because the pegs (of the loom) had not been set for Uttu</l>
        <l n="6">(Because) the ewe had not come forth, the lamb had not multiplied</l>
        <l n="7">(Because) the goat had not come forth, the kid had not multiplied</l>
        <l n="8">(Because) the ewe had not given birth to its lamb</l>
        <l n="9">(Because) the goat had not given birth to its kid</l>
        <l n="10">The names of both Ezina-Kusu (deified grain) and lahar (deified ewe)</l>
        <l n="11">The Anuna, the great gods, did not know</l>
        <l n="12">The muš barley of the thirtieth day was not present</l>
        <l n="13">The muš barley of the fortieth day was not present</l>
        <l n="14">The muš barley of the fiftieth day was not present</l>
        <l n="15">The small barley, the barley of the mountain, the barley of the pure settlement was not present</l>
        <l n="16">Wearing of garments was not present</l>
        <l n="17">Uttu was not yet born, the crown was not yet raised</l>
        <l n="18">Lord Bridegroom (Dumuzi) and Kalkal (the gatekeeper of the Ekur) were not yet born</l>
        <l n="19">Sumuqan had not yet come out in the dry land</l>
        <l n="20">The humans of that distant time</l>
        <l n="21">They did not know that food was to be eaten</l>
        <l n="22">They did not know the wearing of garments</l>
        <l n="23">In the land (one) went/stood (on) limbs (i.e., on all fours?) naked(?)</l>
        <l n="24">Like sheep one ate with grass in its mouth (i.e. ruminated)</l>
        <l n="25">They were drinking water in the ditches(?)</l>
        <l n="26">At that time, at the place of (forming) features of the gods</l>
        <l n="27">In their temple on the Holy Mound ... was creating lahar and Ezina</l>
        <l n="28">They gathered them into the shrine where the gods ate food</l>
        <l n="29">The abundance of lahar and Ašnan</l>
        <l n="30">The Anuna gods of the holy mound</l>
        <l n="31">Were eating(!), but none among them were able to be filled</l>
        <l n="1">The milk/cream of their holy sheepfold, the sweet thing (the Anuna gods of the Holy Mound were drinking, but none among them were able to be filled)</l>
        <l n="2">Humanity ...</l>
        <l n="3">At that time Enki spoke to Enlil</l>
        <l n="4">&quot;Father Enlil, both lahar and Ezina</l>
        <l n="5">Because/after(?)... created (them) on the Holy Mound</l>
        <l n="6">We shall send them down from the Holy Mound”</l>
        <l n="7">This is (how) both(?) Enki and Enlil spoke(?) in their holy conversation</l>
        <l n="8">They(!) were sending down both lahar and Ezina from the Holy Mound</l>
        <l n="9">They(!) were enclosing lahar in her sheepfold</l>
        <l n="10">They were giving vast vegetation to her</l>
        <l n="11">For Ezina they were putting down a fertile field</l>
        <l n="12">They were giving to her the plow, the yoke, and its plow team</l>
        <l n="13">After lahar stood in the sheepfold</l>
        <l n="14">After the shepherd furnished her(?) with allure in the sheepfold</l>
        <l n="15">After Ezina stood in the furrow</l>
        <l n="16">She was a beautiful/verdant young woman bearing allure</l>
        <l n="17">(After) she raised her fertile head in the field</l>
        <l n="18">After she was poured upon by the abundance of heaven(?)</l>
        <l n="19">Both lahar and Ezina appeared</l>
        <l n="20">In heaven abundance was there for them(?)</l>
        <l n="21">In the land life force was there for them(?)</l>
        <l n="22">They were properly executing the me of the gods</l>
        <l n="23">(They were making?) things proliferate in the storehouse(!?) of the land</l>
        <l n="24">Into the prison, founded(!?) (in?) the dust</l>
        <l n="25">After they entered, abundance was there for them</l>
        <l n="26">The two of them (lit. “their two&quot;), where they set their feet</l>
        <l n="27">They are the ones who increase things in the house “heavily”</l>
        <l n="28">Where they stand, they are correct(?), where they sit, they are appropriate</l>
        <l n="29">They are ones that are pleasant in(?) the heart of An and the heart of Enlil</l>
        <l n="30">The were drinking sweet/intoxicating wine</l>
        <l n="31">They were “making (themselves) sweet” (i.e., getting drunk) with sweet/intoxicating beer</l>
        <l n="32">After they drank sweet/intoxicating wine</l>
        <l n="1">Single-column tablet of Damqi-ilišu, month of Abe, 14th day</l>
        <l n="2">(Total:) 62(!) lines</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
