<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000395, ex. 017</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346164</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346164.P346164.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">Therefore shall relax towards its “cool side”</l>
        <l n="2">The male going on the road who (otherwise) spends the night on the road</l>
        <l n="3">Therefore has taken refuge there as if it was his built city</l>
        <l n="4">So that my name is established to distant time, so that it is not dropped by/from the mouth</l>
        <l n="5">So that my praise is performed in the land</l>
        <l n="6">I am possessed of speed, I muster up my strength so that (my) running is tested</l>
        <l n="7">From Nibru to the brickwork of Urim</l>
        <l n="8">Therefore my heart resolved to make the round trip as if (the journey) was one double-hour</l>
        <l n="9">A pirig creature not tiring by means of its youth, I am one who stands by itself(?)</l>
        <l n="10">My little niglam garment was suitable on my hips(?)</l>
        <l n="11">Like a ... wild dove flying furiously, I pumped my arms</l>
        <l n="12">Therefore, like the Anzud bird raising its eye towards its mountain, I spread my knees apart (in stride)</l>
        <l n="13">Therefore the cities of the land that I founded stood for me</l>
        <l n="14">Therefore my black-headed people, teeming like ewes, look to me sweetly</l>
        <l n="1">Like a goat of the mountain range that is running to its dwelling(?)</l>
        <l n="2">(As?) Utu, broadening the daylight upon the settlements</l>
        <l n="3">Therefore I(?) was entering the Ekišnugal temple</l>
        <l n="4">Therefore the temple of Suen, the cattlepen (of) great amounts of butter(?) was filled with abundance</l>
        <l n="5">Therefore bulls were slaughtered there, sheep were slaughtered there</l>
        <l n="6">Therefore the šem and ala drums resounded</l>
        <l n="7">Therefore the tigi drum, the good thing, functioned properly there</l>
        <l n="8">I am Shulgi, the one who makes anything/food(?) numerous and therefore I(?) offered food (offerings) there</l>
        <l n="9">When I roused myself from the ... cultic area like a pirig creature</l>
        <l n="10">It was in the Egalmah temple of Ninegala</l>
        <l n="11">Therefore (I?) relaxed(?) there, (I?) bathed there with flowing water</l>
        <l n="12">Therefore (I?) bend the knee there and ate food there</l>
        <l n="13">Therefore I was arising like a harrier and a falcon</l>
        <l n="14">Therefore I(!?) was returning(?) towards Nibru in my exuberance</l>
        <l n="15">At that time the storm therefore shouted, the stormwind circled</l>
        <l n="16">Therefore the north(?) and south winds howled by themselves</l>
        <l n="17">Therefore flashing lighting wreaked havoc in heaven together with the seven winds</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
