<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000343, ex. 032</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346093</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346093.P346093.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">...</l>
        <l n="2">...</l>
        <l n="3">At that time, Ereškigal slapped her thigh</l>
        <l n="4">She bit her lip and considered the news</l>
        <l n="5">She was speaking to Biti, her chief gatekeeper</l>
        <l n="6">Come, Biti, my chief gatekeeper</l>
        <l n="7">Pay attention to what I have said to you</l>
        <l n="8">She(?) shall drag the bolts of the seven gates of the netherworld from (their lock?)</l>
        <l n="9">She(?) shall push the single door of the palace of Ganzer push (open)</l>
        <l n="1">The man took away her split apart skin(?)</l>
        <l n="2">What (is going on/is this/he (doing))(?)?</l>
        <l n="3">Be satisfied, Inanna! This is the rite of the netherworld that is being completed</l>
        <l n="4">Inanna! This is the procedure of the netherworld, you should not speak aloud</l>
        <l n="5">When she bent down/died, ... her</l>
        <l n="6">Her sister raised her up from her throne</l>
        <l n="7">She sat down apart from her throne</l>
        <l n="8">The seven judges of the Anuna were judging her</l>
        <l n="9">Their decision(?) was one of embittered anger</l>
        <l n="10">..., it was embittered anger</l>
        <l n="11">... struck her and turned her into a smitten piece of meat</l>
        <l n="12">The man hung her face/front(?) from(!) a crossbeam(?)</l>
        <l n="13">After seven years, seven months, and seven days elapsed</l>
        <l n="14">Her vizier Ninšubur paid attention to the word of her lady</l>
        <l n="15">She repeatedly made “the lament of ruin heaps” for her</l>
        <l n="16">She played the šem drum of the assembly/throne room for her</l>
        <l n="17">She circled the temples of the gods for her</l>
        <l n="18">She scratched her face, she scratched her nose</l>
        <l n="19">The place unseen (when) with a man, she scratched her (inner) thigh</l>
        <l n="20">...</l>
        <l n="1'">...</l>
        <l n="2'">...</l>
        <l n="3'">Her fingernails were lodged (in her flesh)(?) like lubi axes/agricultural implements</l>
        <l n="4'">She trimmedthe hair on her head like leeks</l>
        <l n="5'">When she says “alas, my (heart/liver)”</l>
        <l n="6'">They said to her “you are weary, our lady (is the reason for?) your 'alas, (my) liver'&quot;(?)</l>
        <l n="7'">Who are you?</l>
        <l n="8'">From my heart to your heart, from my liver(?) to your liver(?), ...</l>
        <l n="9'">If you are a god, I shall speak to you(?)</l>
        <l n="10'">If you are human, I shall decree a fate (of death) for you</l>
        <l n="11'">They swore by the life of heaven and earth (that they were gods)</l>
        <l n="12'">... were to go/bring out/up(?)</l>
        <l n="13'">Water of the river was offered to them but not accepted</l>
        <l n="14'">Barley of the field was offered to them but not accepted</l>
        <l n="15'">They were saying to her “give us the beaten meat hanging from the beam”</l>
        <l n="16'">... the meat that was beaten was that of their(!) lady</l>
        <l n="17'">They were saying “give it, whether it pertains to our king or our lady”</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
