<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>UET 6, 0151</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346236</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346236.P346236.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">Why do you behave like this?</l>
        <l n="2">One has rejected the other, cursed the other, insulted the other</l>
        <l n="3">You put an outcry in the scribal school</l>
        <l n="4">&quot;By (the possessor of?) a truthful heart he been taught(?) Sumerian</l>
        <l n="5">The one who, he ... away from(?) the assignment” it was said</l>
        <l n="6">The sheaf that was not threshed, his ... which did not fall off(?)</l>
        <l n="7">You should be beaten on account of (the output of) this daily assignment, ...</l>
        <l n="8">The outcry has not(!) been a regular occurrence(?)</l>
        <l n="9">Why, the one who is your “big brother”</l>
        <l n="10">And the one who knows the scribal art better than you</l>
        <l n="11">Why did you speak with (empty?) praise(?)</l>
        <l n="12">You have offended(?) him, you have cursed him, you have insulted him</l>
        <l n="13">The master did(?) everything</l>
        <l n="14">And grew exceedingly angry (saying?) “do as you wish”</l>
        <l n="15">If you do as you wish</l>
        <l n="15">For this auxiliary construction see Attinger ZA 95, 244.</l>
        <l n="16">Because of the fact that the one who acted like you offended(?) his “big brother”</l>
        <l n="17">After being struck with the “tablet shaping board” (as) a weapon sixty times</l>
        <l n="18">After chains were placed on his feet</l>
        <l n="19">He was confined in the house and did not leave the scribal school for two months</l>
        <l n="1">Now, the sin has been released for you</l>
        <l n="2">From this day onwards, their faces have been incised</l>
        <l n="3">Do not behave insultingly to each other(?)</l>
        <l n="4">Do not speak out(?) brother with (against) brother, do not initiate legal proceedings (against each other)</l>
        <l n="5">(As for) the quarrel of both Girini'isag and Enkimanšum</l>
        <l n="6">The master arrives at a verdict(?) for them</l>
        <l n="7">Nisaba, praise!</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
