<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000356, ex. 003</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346108</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346108.P346108.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">Get up in order to sail, get up in order to sail, ...</l>
        <l n="2">(several lines missing)</l>
        <l n="3">Ištarān, with the face of šuba stones, his mother is to receive the downstream sailing barge(?)</l>
        <l n="4'">Alla, lugalsapar, the barge that his mother is to receive (in the netherworld)(?)</l>
        <l n="5'">LugalKANE, his mother is to receive the downstream sailing barge(?)</l>
        <l n="6'">Ningešzida, his mother is to receive the downstream sailing barge(?)</l>
        <l n="7'">His younger sister sang a lament in the cabin at the front of the boat</l>
        <l n="8'">His older sister ... in the cabin at the rear of the boat</l>
        <l n="9'">I want to sail with you, I want to sail with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="10'">My brother, I want to ride your barge with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="11'">I want to ride(?) your ...</l>
        <l n="12'">At the front of the boat I shall intone a lament/seize the ladder(?), I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="13'">At the back of the boat I shall kill (intruders?)(?), I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="14'">Youth Damu, I want to sail with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="15'">..., I want to sail with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="16'">Ištarān, with the face/eye of šuba stones, I want to sail with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="17'">Alla, lugalsapar (lord of the net), I want to sail with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="18'">LugalKANE, I want to sail with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="19'">Ningešzida, I want to sail with you, my brother, I want to sail with you</l>
        <l n="20'">The evil galla demon dwelling in the middle was speaking to Ningešzida</l>
        <l n="21'">Lugalkisuna, look at your sister</l>
        <l n="22'">Lugalkisuna, having looked at his sister, was speaking to her</l>
        <l n="23'">I have ridden with him, I have ridden with him, why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="24'">My sister, I have ridden with my galla demon, why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="25'">I have ridden with my man who pelts (me), why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="26'">I have ridden with my man who binds (my) hands, why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="27'">I have ridden with my man who binds (my) arms, why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="1">The river of the netherworld does not convey water/irrigate, its water is not drunk/it is not full of water(?), why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="2">The field of the netherworld does not grow barley, flour is not ground(?) (utilizing it), why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="3">The sheep of the netherworld does not wear wool, a garment is not woven (utilizing it), why are you to sail (with me)?</l>
        <l n="4">(Because of this journey?) I, whom my mother excavated like a canal/planted on the river (bank)(!?), my water is not drunk(?)</l>
        <l n="5">I(?) am not watered by hand like a tamarisk, no one sits in my shade(?)</l>
        <l n="6">No one(?) ... the allure of my date-bearing like a date palm</l>
        <l n="7">My galla demon gouged(?) with a stick(?), causing you to scream</l>
        <l n="8">He placed ... on my hands, causing you to scream</l>
        <l n="9'">He placed ... on my neck, causing you to scream</l>
        <l n="10'">Amašilama was speaking to? Ningešzida</l>
        <l n="11'">If(?) ... makes a gift(?) for(?) the grievous(?) ..., ...</l>
        <l n="12'">If(?) ... makes a gift(?) for(?) your galla demon ...</l>
        <l n="13'">I want to ..., it is becoming too much for you</l>
        <l n="14'">I want to ..., it is becoming too much for you</l>
        <l n="15'">I want to ... the little ones(?) (on?) my lap, it is becoming too much for you</l>
        <l n="16'">I want to ... (on?) my lap like my(?) ..., it is becoming too much for you</l>
        <l n="17'">I(?) am ..., ..., it is becoming too much for you</l>
        <l n="18'">My brother, you have been acted upon(?), my brother, you have been acted upon(?), it is becoming too much for you</l>
        <l n="19'">..., you have been acted upon(?), my brother, you have been acted upon(?), it is becoming too much for you</l>
        <l n="20'">... the stern(?) ...</l>
        <l n="21'">...</l>
        <l n="22'">...</l>
        <l n="23'">... the stern(?) ...</l>
        <l n="24'">... encircled you(?), ...</l>
        <l n="26'">...</l>
        <l n="27'">..., sequester yourself in your house, city(!)/southern storm(?), sequester yourself in your house</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
