<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000510, ex. 001</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346187</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346187.P346187.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">Shepherd nominated by holy An, (for whom) a great fate was determined in heaven</l>
        <l n="2">Rīm-Sîn, nominated by holy An, (for who) a great fate was determined in heaven</l>
        <l n="3">The ruler has attained/met (the demands of)(?) the kingship from (the moment he emerged from) the fertile womb</l>
        <l n="4">You are the one who(?) continually executes/pursues(?) the en-ship greatly on behalf of the many people</l>
        <l n="5">In larsa, ... mountain that fashions(?) the cosmic power of rulership</l>
        <l n="6">You have been faithfully chosen for the shepherdship of Sumer and Akkad</l>
        <l n="7">Great An, supreme one of the universe, lord who is wise (in) everything</l>
        <l n="8">Father of the gods who looks to determine fate on behalf of its place</l>
        <l n="9">(Whose) command is weighty, his(!?) word cannot be replied to(?)</l>
        <l n="10">... in the holy midst of heaven</l>
        <l n="11">Ruler Rīm-Sîn, you are the shepherd who is to come out in the midst (of the people)(?)/make (his) intentions clear(?)</l>
        <l n="12">And therefore great An made his loving heart shine for you</l>
        <l n="13">Because of your justice, he(!) spoke faithfully to you</l>
        <l n="14">In(?) the distant midst of heaven, the days of your life shall be made surpassing for you</l>
        <l n="15">Kingship of the vast land has been made supreme for you for a long time</l>
        <l n="16">In their holy mouths a fate of life has been decided for you</l>
        <l n="17">With(?) the utterance from which nothing is to be changed a long life shall be added for you</l>
        <l n="18">The holy crown shall be firm upon your head</l>
        <l n="19">The throne of life shall be seated down(!?) greatly for you</l>
        <l n="20">The uluh scepter shall be given over to your hand</l>
        <l n="21">The nose-rope(?) that solidifies the land has been fastened to your flesh(!?)</l>
        <l n="22">The staff shall seize/pasture(?) the teeming people for you</l>
        <l n="23">The breast of shining heaven shall be opened for you, the rain of heaven shall be poured for you</l>
        <l n="24">A year of abundance and a day of plenty shall be arrayed(?) ... the midst of heaven(!?) for you</l>
        <l n="25">A month/moonlight(?), that of joy and rejoicing, shall be established for you on behalf of your days/time</l>
        <l n="1">A good reign, surpassing in justice(?), shall be placed at your disposal</l>
        <l n="2">Great An protecting you profoundly, this shall be (what characterizes) your kingship</l>
        <l n="3">Rīm-Sîn, my king</l>
        <l n="4">28 (are) its lines</l>
        <l n="5">šude prayer of An</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
