<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000820, ex. 001</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346384</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346384.P346384.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="2">The weapon is not one that utters his name, it is one that finds his flesh</l>
        <l n="4">If the city changes (its) name/year(?), I would (have to) affirm my name/year(?)</l>
        <l n="5">The mongoose does not know the aura of divinity</l>
        <l n="7">Follow your lot and make your mother rejoice, run(?) and make your god rejoice</l>
        <l n="8">The buzzard entered the mouth of a corpse(?)</l>
        <l n="9">The fly is the one that enters, your mouth is the one that strikes/jumps?</l>
        <l n="12">If the scepter slaughters the bull, if the whip slaughters the sheep, in the place where there is no assembly/mourning place(?), the man who is not seated(?), he is a vizier single ruling?</l>
        <l n="13">If ... pours oil inside a scepter, (no one will know)</l>
        <l n="16">The person who has not valued his god, his corpse is not buried, his heir does not pour water, his ghost does not drink</l>
        <l n="17">May/if ... stands for me(?) ...</l>
        <l n="18">The weeping of the female laborer ...</l>
        <l n="19">The child of the female laborer, the spouse of the female laborer? ...</l>
        <l n="20">A boat does not ... her(?) marsh</l>
        <l n="21">(On?) the bank(?) ... of her(?) marsh(?) reed(s) do not(?) ...</l>
        <l n="22">...</l>
        <l n="23">...</l>
        <l n="1'">...</l>
        <l n="2'">A malicious spouse ...</l>
        <l n="3'">Illness? ...</l>
        <l n="4'">... that does not have a house ...</l>
        <l n="6'">... to not ...dust/earth(?), it is anthema of Utu</l>
        <l n="8'">A man going about is one who has found something, a woman going about has lost something</l>
        <l n="10'">If a hireling who parches grain returns/answers, (his) head is smoking(?)</l>
        <l n="13'">The prison is a thicket, the king is a lion, Nungal is a šuša net covering the young men</l>
        <l n="15'">Having left the house and entered into(?) the street, the female worker set up a banquet apart from her lady</l>
        <l n="17'">No barley being present is the (destructive) hand(?) of the city, no reeds being present is extreme poverty/execessive neighborliness(?)</l>
        <l n="19'">&quot;I am bent at the thigh” is what the leatherworker (says)(?), “By the life of Enki, murky water flows (away?)” is what the fuller (says)(?)</l>
        <l n="22'">May(?) the hot fish cool for you, the bones gathered from the fish ... I ...</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
