<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000757, ex. 003</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346252</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346252.P346252.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">Young man, are you a student of the eduba'a? (Yes,) I am a student of the eduba'a</l>
        <l n="2">If you are a student of the eduba'a</l>
        <l n="3">Do you know Sumerian?</l>
        <l n="4">I can converse by means of Sumerian</l>
        <l n="5">... (if) you are young/junior, how can you converse in/translate your ...</l>
        <l n="6">If I hear that of the mouth of my master once or twice</l>
        <l n="7">I can repeat that speech (lit. answer) for you</l>
        <l n="8">(But even) if your reproduction of that is present, what will you write?</l>
        <l n="9">If you(?) inquire after that which I write (you will find out that)</l>
        <l n="10">... my dwelling in the eduba'a ... could not have been less than three months(?)</l>
        <l n="11">... of Sumer and Akkad, from the “syllable alphabet(s)” a-a (Syllable Alphabet B) and me-me (Syllable Alphabet A)</l>
        <l n="12">To ... (I) counted out (the number of lines in a given manuscript?) and (I) wrote</l>
        <l n="13">From the various entries/names of (the personal name list) Inanna</l>
        <l n="14">Until “the animals of the steppe” (commentary or perhaps the ur5-ra list of animals) to the end of “person” (=) “he” (the lexical list lu2 = ša), (I) wrote</l>
        <l n="15">I can find their signs</l>
        <l n="16">Thus I explain their writings and solutions</l>
        <l n="17">Follow me (lit. seize behind me)</l>
        <l n="18">I cannot block anything for you</l>
        <l n="19">And the (extract of) the professions list lu2 = šu that was assigned to me on my “hand tablet”</l>
        <l n="20">I(?) can produce a sequence of six hundred entries</l>
        <l n="21">The account of my days residing in the school are established</l>
        <l n="1">My idle days are three days per month</l>
        <l n="2">The various festivals are three days per month</l>
        <l n="3">In the midst (of what remains) in the month there are 24 days</l>
        <l n="4">My dwelling in the school is not (measured with) deductible days</l>
        <l n="5">In each single day, my master (requires) that I produce my nigsuru assignment(?) 4 times</l>
        <l n="6">The account having been established, my knowledge of the scribal art is not taken away(?)</l>
        <l n="7">Now I can apply myself(?) to the contents of tablets, to multiplication tables and calculations(?)</l>
        <l n="8">The scribal art, putting entries (in their context)(!?), without(?) nigsuru assignments(?) ...</l>
        <l n="9">My master, speaking pleasantly, (his) prayer (on my behalf!?)</l>
        <l n="10">(His) treating (me) as a colleague, it is something that is to make the heart rejoice</l>
        <l n="11">I know my scribal art</l>
        <l n="12">I do not restrict ... concerning anything</l>
        <l n="13">My master selects one sign</l>
        <l n="14">From my memory I add one or two (more)</l>
        <l n="15">At the agreed point, after I reside (there)</l>
        <l n="16">Regarding the Sumerian language, the scribal art, (its) content, counting and accounting(?)</l>
        <l n="17">I equal you</l>
        <l n="18">I (would) converse with you by means of Sumerian</l>
        <l n="19">But (even) if it (the option of my answering!?) is present(?), on account of the fact that Sumerian is obscure for you</l>
        <l n="20">I shall go to write a tablet (instead)</l>
        <l n="21">The tablet of one gur of barley until 600 gur of barley (metrological table)</l>
        <l n="22">The tablet of one gin silver until 10 mana of silver (metrological table)</l>
        <l n="23">Partnership (model contracts), so that one can choose (to include) the inspection of a one gun amount (of silver)</l>
        <l n="24">Purchasing a house, field, orchard, or male or female slave (model contracts)</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
