<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000365, ex. 024</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346135</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346135.P346135.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1'">The 5th is ..., a screaming sagkal snake, ...(?), splitting the mountain range</l>
        <l n="2'">The 6th is ..., beating its breast against the mountain like a flood</l>
        <l n="3'">The 7th is ... flashing like lightning(!), no one will approach its side</l>
        <l n="4'">The seven heroes, the youth Utu gave to Gilgamesh</l>
        <l n="5'">They(?) will bring the boats for portage to the base of the mountain range</l>
        <l n="6'">It was made pleasing there for the one who cuts the juniper</l>
        <l n="7'">It was made pleasing there for lord Gilgamesh</l>
        <l n="8'">In his city as a single man he sounded the horn</l>
        <l n="9'">As two companions (he and Enkidu), (they) shouted together</l>
        <l n="10'">The one who has a household to his household, the one who has (lives with) a mother to his mother</l>
        <l n="11'">May single males acting(?) like me, act on behalf of my power</l>
        <l n="12'">The one who has a household to his household, the one who has (lives with) a mother to his mother</l>
        <l n="13'">The single males acting(?) like me, fifty of them, have acted on behalf of my power</l>
        <l n="14'">He set out to the house of the blacksmith</l>
        <l n="15'">He was pouring (the metal for) the (blade of the) a'ašgar ax, the agasilig axe(!?), the arms of heroism</l>
        <l n="16'">He set out to the grove of deep shade</l>
        <l n="17'">He was striking (down) the axe handle(?) of halub wood, apple wood, and boxwood</l>
        <l n="18'">...</l>
        <l n="1'">No one can cut a three-ply rope(?)</l>
        <l n="2'">On a wall, water does not overwhelm a man(?)</l>
        <l n="3'">Fire cannot be extinguished in a house with a reed fence</l>
        <l n="4'">You help me, I shall help you, what is it of ours that someone can take (away)?</l>
        <l n="5'">When it sank, when it sank</l>
        <l n="6'">When the Magan boat sank</l>
        <l n="7'">When the barge(?), Magilum, sank</l>
        <l n="8'">A raft, a lifeboat, seized ...</l>
        <l n="9'">Come! let us go and have a look!</l>
        <l n="10'">(But) if we go</l>
        <l n="11'">There will be an aura, there will be an aura, turn back!</l>
        <l n="12'">There will be cunning(?) there will be cunning, turn back!</l>
        <l n="13'">(This is) your thought, (but) come, let's go!</l>
        <l n="14'">After someone has not even approached (within) 3600(?) ninda</l>
        <l n="15'">Huwawa has (already) “seized” (him in) his house of juniper/cedar</l>
        <l n="16'">He has looked, it is the look of death</l>
        <l n="17'">He has shaken his head (taking an oath?), its is a head filled with (punishment for?) sin</l>
        <l n="18'">You who are a young man to your detriment, you will not return to the city of your mother</l>
        <l n="19'">He imposed his aura into his muscles and his feet</l>
        <l n="20'">He could not turn his foot (i.e., take a step) on the ground</l>
        <l n="1'">Huwawa by means of his own strength ..., he said? to him “sit”</l>
        <l n="2'">The hero(!) sat down, wept, and made sobbing noises</l>
        <l n="3'">Huwawa sat down, wept, and made sobbing noises</l>
        <l n="4'">Huwawa ... compassion for Gilgamesh</l>
        <l n="5'">Gilgamesh, release me!</l>
        <l n="6'">So that I may speak a word with Utu</l>
        <l n="7'">Utu, (I) do not know the mother that bore me, (I) do not know the father that reared me</l>
        <l n="8'">I was born in the mountain, you reared me</l>
        <l n="9'">Gilgamesh swore an oath by heaven, he swore an oath by earth, he swore an oath by the netherworld</l>
        <l n="10'">He seized his hand(?), (saying): “you shall not be deprived”</l>
        <l n="11'">At that time, Gilgamesh, the native, had compassion in his heart</l>
        <l n="12'">Gilgamesh was speaking to Enkidu</l>
        <l n="13'">Enkidu, may the captured bird go (back) to its place for me(?)</l>
        <l n="14'">May the captured youth be returned to the lap of his mother</l>
        <l n="15'">His servant Enkidu was replying</l>
        <l n="16'">The tall, (if) he lacks intellect</l>
        <l n="17'">The Namtar demon/fate will consume him, the Namtar demon/fate having not been revealed</l>
        <l n="18'">The caught bird that is to go back to its place</l>
        <l n="19'">The caught youth that is to be returned to the lap of its mother</l>
        <l n="20'">You will not return to the city of your birth mother</l>
        <l n="21'">...</l>
        <l n="22'">Huwawa was speaking to Enkidu</l>
        <l n="23'">Enkidu is defaming me</l>
        <l n="24'">...</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
