<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000472, ex. 001</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346203</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346203.P346203.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="2">City, your aura covers the universe</l>
        <l n="3">Your might is supreme and surpassing</l>
        <l n="4">Shrine Nibru</l>
        <l n="5">Wherever the heavens cover (i.e., everywhere)</l>
        <l n="6">Your strength is there (all the way to) its boundaries</l>
        <l n="8">(Among) all of the brick (structures) founded in the land</l>
        <l n="9">Your brickwork is the foremost brickwork</l>
        <l n="12">The lands accept the supreme cosmic powers in all their cities</l>
        <l n="13">Like your supreme cosmic powers,</l>
        <l n="14">your reputation is supreme</l>
        <l n="15">Like your reputation,</l>
        <l n="16">your soil is good soil</l>
        <l n="18">City, your name is surpassing in the universe</l>
        <l n="19">You are the bond</l>
        <l n="20">of the lowlands and highlands,</l>
        <l n="21">the great pillar of the many people</l>
        <l n="22">Your cosmic powers are clever and</l>
        <l n="23">that cannot be dispersed</l>
        <l n="24">And thus your plans,</l>
        <l n="25">like something that occupies the subterranean waters,</l>
        <l n="26">And thus your plans, like something that occupies the subterranean waters, emit a great aura</l>
        <l n="1">your greatness,</l>
        <l n="2">which is verdant like the goddess Uraš (earth personified)</l>
        <l n="3">No one is to ascertain.</l>
        <l n="4">Your fate,</l>
        <l n="5">going out at the forefront,</l>
        <l n="6">is something that surpasses (any) praise</l>
        <l n="7">A high mountain range</l>
        <l n="8">that no hand can approach are you.</l>
        <l n="9">Head raised high, surpassing</l>
        <l n="10">You are touching heaven</l>
        <l n="11">Your interior is powerful</l>
        <l n="12">Your exterior</l>
        <l n="13">is filled with awe</l>
        <l n="17">And thus you produce food (for) the Anuna for their lives</l>
        <l n="19">You are verdant for their eating and drinking</l>
        <l n="20">You are the sheepfold that is there for their breath</l>
        <l n="23">Nothing can escape from you arm, which is like the extended cords of a net</l>
        <l n="25">Shrine Nibru, your way is that of greatness</l>
        <l n="26">Surpassing description</l>
        <l n="1">When you divide up the cosmic powers (it results in) a true lot that cannot be dispelled</l>
        <l n="3">City, your inside is pure</l>
        <l n="4">Your outside is pure</l>
        <l n="6">Your body bears an aura</l>
        <l n="7">Your site is a chosen(?) place</l>
        <l n="10">The lord of wisdom, the Great Mountain Enlil, has built a shrine in your midst</l>
        <l n="13">That shrine, the sparkling shrine, it is the shrine that is to determine fate</l>
        <l n="16">The Ekur, the sparkling temple, it is the temple that is to determine fate</l>
        <l n="19">Your ruler, Nunamnir, the young bull who inseminates the cosmic powers</l>
        <l n="22">Mother Ninlil, the great queen of the Ki'ur complex, lady who gave birth to the cosmic powers</l>
        <l n="26">What other god lives in the land like he and she?</l>
        <l n="29">They have wrapped themselves with intelligence and counsel at the place of dusk</l>
        <l n="2">They have sat down (in their thrones) with a reddish hue(?)</l>
        <l n="5">They have sat down (in their thrones) among the true cosmic powers, the great powers, the cosmic powers of praise</l>
        <l n="8">The Anuna gods look to them as their birth parents</l>
        <l n="12">And therefore they listen to their pure and most precious words, uttered faithfully</l>
        <l n="16">Both Enlil and Ninlil looked at the sky</l>
        <l n="18">They made a (temporary) sanctuary(?) on the earth (according to the stars they saw)</l>
        <l n="22">At that time, the intentions for the broad earth that great An had brought forth (for Enlil and Ninlil to see)</l>
        <l n="25">The Anuna gods of heaven and earth set to work (to fulfill them)</l>
        <l n="30">The hoe and the earth-moving basket, those (tools) which establish a city, were ... in their hands</l>
        <l n="31">... Haya(?) and Nisaba</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
