<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000351, ex. 046</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346089</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346089.P346089.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">The mountain shall make the livestock teem for you</l>
        <l n="2">The mountain range shall make the quadrupeds proliferate for you</l>
        <l n="3">You, a lady with whose cosmic powers no other cosmic powers compare, who wears a furious/reddish aura like heaven</l>
        <l n="4">Digirmah, who hates excessive speech</l>
        <l n="5">The true lady, Ninhursag, the young woman</l>
        <l n="6">Nintur, who ... when it cools (in the evening?)</l>
        <l n="7">Draw near(?), lady, I(!) have given you supreme cosmic powers so that you shall be exalted/shall wield them</l>
        <l n="8">True lady(!?), her cosmic powers surpass (other) cosmic powers, lady, “carpenter of the womb”</l>
        <l n="9">Aruru, the elder sister of Enlil, stood at his front</l>
        <l n="10">&quot;Great hero, when you killed the hero</l>
        <l n="11">Lord, who like his father his utterance cannot be changed, you have not (yet) decreed a fate”</l>
        <l n="12">The lord was speaking to the emery stone, he was wishing for/observing (its) path(?)</l>
        <l n="13">In the homeland, the angry lord(?) spoke a word to him</l>
        <l n="14">Ninurta, lord, son of Enlil was cursing him</l>
        <l n="15">Emery stone, you who (the Asag) mustered against me in the mountain</l>
        <l n="1">As one who seized ... in order to render/place my hands(?) ...</l>
        <l n="2">As one who swore to commit(?) my murder</l>
        <l n="3">As one who terrified me, lord Ninurta, in my own supreme dwelling</l>
        <l n="4">Mighty one, youth possessed of form, your surpassing(ness) and you stature shall be diminished</l>
        <l n="5">Leopards that rely on their strength shall tear you up</l>
        <l n="6">The powerful one shall accept a test of strength(?) (with you)</l>
        <l n="7">Young man emery, your brother(s) shall heap you like flour</l>
        <l n="8">You, young man, your shout shall be present and tremble(!?), (but) it shall end(?)</l>
        <l n="9">You shall raise a hand (violently) against your offspring, show the teeth against their corpses!</l>
        <l n="10">Like a great bull killed by many men/a slaughterer(?), make (yourself) into/set (yourself) apart as(!?) something divided into shares(?)</l>
        <l n="11">Emery, by means of(?) the weapon dog, away from battle,</l>
        <l n="12">like something chased away by the junior shepherd</l>
        <l n="13">I am the lord, (you) shall be named according to(?) your having pecked at/demolished(?) carnelian</l>
        <l n="14">Now, (this) is the decreed fate of Ninurta</l>
        <l n="15">Today (and henceforth), when emery touches (another stone), it will be in order to perforate carnelian, thus it is so!</l>
        <l n="16">The hero was speaking to the šu'u and gasura stones</l>
        <l n="17">...</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
