<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000364, ex. 047</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346140</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346140.P346140.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">Those distant days, those distant remote days</l>
        <l n="2">Those distant nights, those distant remote nights</l>
        <l n="3">Those distant years, those distant remote years</l>
        <l n="4">At that time, when a primeval entity was made manifest</l>
        <l n="5">At that ancient time, when a primeval entity was cared for</l>
        <l n="6">When bread was “tasted?” (lit. “covered&quot;) in the shrine(s) of the land</l>
        <l n="7">When the firebox was prepared(?) in the oven(s) of the land</l>
        <l n="8">When heaven had been separated from earth</l>
        <l n="9">When earth had been separated from heaven</l>
        <l n="10">When ... established the name of humanity on ...</l>
        <l n="11">When An had brought away the sky</l>
        <l n="12">When Enlil had brought away the earth</l>
        <l n="13">When ... gifted that of the netherworld on behalf of Ereškigal/When that of the netherworld was gifted on behalf of Ereškigal</l>
        <l n="14">When he rode, when he rode</l>
        <l n="15">When the father rode towards the netherworld</l>
        <l n="16">When Enki rode towards the netherworld</l>
        <l n="17">For the king, ... cast down the small (stones)</l>
        <l n="18">For Enki, ... cast down the large (stones)</l>
        <l n="19">The little ones were hammer-stones/hand-sized stones(?)</l>
        <l n="20">The large ones were stones that made the reeds shake</l>
        <l n="21">It was the keel of the little boat of Enki</l>
        <l n="22">The bobbing turtle, was overwhelmed</l>
        <l n="23">For the king, the water of the prow</l>
        <l n="24">Was attacking in a pack like wolves</l>
        <l n="25">For Enki the water of the stern</l>
        <l n="26">Was slaughtering like a lion</l>
        <l n="27">At that time, there was a single tree, a halub tree</l>
        <l n="28">The one that was planted on the bank of the Euphrates(!?)</l>
        <l n="29">The one that was to drink water (from) the Euphrates(?)</l>
        <l n="30">The power of the southern wind tore it out at its roots, it ripped it out its branches(?)</l>
        <l n="1">The Euphrates struck it with (flood)water</l>
        <l n="2">The woman, who was fearing(?) the command of An, was coming (by)</l>
        <l n="3">Fearing(?) the command of Enlil, was coming by</l>
        <l n="4">She grasped the tree in her hand and brought it to Uruk</l>
        <l n="5">She was bringing it towards the flowering orchard of Inanna</l>
        <l n="6-7">The woman did not plant the tree as it was in(?) her hand, it was by means of her foot that she planted it</l>
        <l n="8-9">The woman did not water the tree as it was in(?) her hand, it was by means of her foot that she watered it</l>
        <l n="10">She said “When am I to sit on its flowering throne?”</l>
        <l n="11">She said “When am I to I lie down on its flowering bed?”</l>
        <l n="12">The wood thickened, but its bark could not be split</l>
        <l n="13">At its base a snake that was immune to incantations made a nest</l>
        <l n="14">In its branches the Anzu bird placed (its) chick</l>
        <l n="15">The demon maiden of the empty wind made a house in its middle</l>
        <l n="16">The laughing, rejoicing young woman</l>
        <l n="17">Holy Inanna, how she was weeping</l>
        <l n="18">The day was about to break, the horizon was about to light up</l>
        <l n="19">The little birds at daybreak were about to shriek</l>
        <l n="20">When Utu came out from his chamber</l>
        <l n="21">His sister, to the hero Utu</l>
        <l n="22">Holy Inanna was speaking</l>
        <l n="23">My brother, long ago, when fate was decreed</l>
        <l n="24">When days of abundance elapsed in the land</l>
        <l n="25">When An had brought away the sky</l>
        <l n="26">When Enlil had brought away the earth</l>
        <l n="27">When ... gifted that of the netherworld on behalf of Ereškigal/When that of the netherworld was gifted on behalf of Ereškigal</l>
        <l n="28">When he rode, when he rode</l>
        <l n="29">When the father rode towards the netherworld</l>
        <l n="30">When Enki rode towards the netherworld</l>
        <l n="31">For the lord, ... cast down the small (stones)</l>
        <l n="32">For Enki, ... cast down the large (stones)</l>
        <l n="33">The little ones were hammer-stones/hand-sized stones(?)</l>
        <l n="1">Month of NENEgar, 26th day</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
