<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000347, ex. 009</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346104</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346104.P346104.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">If my friend dropped his head in the plants then no one can know his place</l>
        <l n="2">Dumuzi! They were seeking his head in the plants, no one found him</l>
        <l n="3">If he dropped his head in the tiny plants then no one can know his place</l>
        <l n="4">Dumuzi! They were seeking his head in the tiny plants, no one found him</l>
        <l n="5">If he dropped his head in the large plants then no one can know his place</l>
        <l n="6">Dumuzi! They were seeking his head in the large plants, no one found him</l>
        <l n="7">If he dropped (his) head in the dikes of Arali then no one can know his place</l>
        <l n="8">Dumuzi! They were catching him in the dikes of Arali</l>
        <l n="9">Dumuzi wept and made sobbing noises</l>
        <l n="10">My sister sustained me in the city, my friend killed me in the city</l>
        <l n="11">May my sister station (her) son in the street, and may he be kissed</l>
        <l n="12">May (my) friend station (his) son in the street, and may he not be kissed</l>
        <l n="13">They surrounded the man, they ... the reservoir</l>
        <l n="14">They were braiding a cord for him, they were knotting a net for him</l>
        <l n="15">They were braiding the zippatum cord for him</l>
        <l n="16">They were “scratching&quot;(?) sticks of manu wood for him</l>
        <l n="17">The man before him was pelting him</l>
        <l n="18">The man behind him was pulling him out (from his hiding place) as (if he was merely?) one cubit (tall?)</l>
        <l n="19.a">His hands were seized in handcuffs,</l>
        <l n="19.b">his arms were bound in manacles</l>
        <l n="20">The young man raised his hands heavenward for Utu</l>
        <l n="21">Utu, you are my brother in law, I am your in-law</l>
        <l n="22">You are my food carrier to the Eanna temple</l>
        <l n="1">I am the one who made a betrothal gift in Uruk</l>
        <l n="2">I am the one who kissed the holy lips</l>
        <l n="3">I am the one who played on the holy knees, the knees of Inanna</l>
        <l n="4">After you have prepared my hands as the hands of a gazelle</l>
        <l n="5">After you have prepared my feet as the feet of a gazelle</l>
        <l n="6">I want to run for my life towards ...</l>
        <l n="7">Utu accepted his tears as a kadra gift</l>
        <l n="8">Like a compassionate person he ... mercy</l>
        <l n="9">After he prepared his hands as the hands of a gazelle</l>
        <l n="10">After he prepared his feet as the feet of a gazelle</l>
        <l n="11">He ran for his life towards ...</l>
        <l n="12">The galla demons were seeking him, no one was finding him</l>
        <l n="13">Come, let us go to ...</l>
        <l n="14">Dumuzi! They seized him at ...</l>
        <l n="15">They encircled the man and ... the reservoir</l>
        <l n="16">They were braiding a cord for him, they were knotting a net for him</l>
        <l n="17">They were braiding the zippatum cord for him</l>
        <l n="18">They were “scratching&quot;(!?) sticks of manu wood for him</l>
        <l n="19">The man before him was pelting him</l>
        <l n="20">The man behind him was pulling him out (from his hiding place) as (if he was merely?) one cuibit (tall?)</l>
        <l n="21.a">His hands were seized in handcuffs,</l>
        <l n="21.b">his arms were bound in manacles</l>
        <l n="22">The young man raised his hands heavenward for Utu</l>
        <l n="23">Utu, you are my brother in law, I am your in-law</l>
        <l n="24">You are my food carrier to the Eanna temple</l>
        <l n="25">I am the one who made a betrothal gift in Uruk</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
