<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000389, ex. 001</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346162</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346162.P346162.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1'">Where in Sumer and Akkad will Nunamnir chose?</l>
        <l n="2'">In Nippur, at the “mountain range of life,” he decreed my(!?) fate</l>
        <l n="3'">At Ur, it being in the Emudkura shrine</l>
        <l n="4'">He secured the foundations of his throne</l>
        <l n="5'">The crown and the (accompanying) aura, (eliciting) the “praise” of kingship, he(!?) put on my(?) head</l>
        <l n="6'">He made the pure scepter that puts the many people in order the equal of my hand(?)</l>
        <l n="7'">He gave to my hand ... and the nose-rope that convey the people</l>
        <l n="8'">... the temple to be admired(?) he put in order(?)</l>
        <l n="9'">...</l>
        <l n="1'">The gizi reed growth, “standing in silver&quot;(?), flourishes</l>
        <l n="2'">My canal(?) (that furnishes?) a day of abundance, a reign(?) of ..., the “pure ...” canal is named</l>
        <l n="3'">Named an everlasting name that is suitable for the mouth, the “its (outlying) ditches are clean” canal is named</l>
        <l n="4'">(As for?) me, the way of (the canal of?) my city is fish(?), its float/excess(?) is birds</l>
        <l n="5'">The “pure ...” canal, it flow(!?) is fish(?), its float/excess(?) is birds</l>
        <l n="6'">The canal whose (outlying) ditches are clean, its flow is fish(?), its float/excess(?) is birds</l>
        <l n="7'">Abundantly it brought fish to the Ekišnugal temple</l>
        <l n="8'">... (on its banks) are munzer plants which one eats (like?) the “honey plant”</l>
        <l n="9'">Making mottled barley/crops grow in its meadows (so that it) sways like a forest/for it to be denuded (at harvest time) like a forest(?)</l>
        <l n="10'">The king of the four regions, obedient one of Enlil</l>
        <l n="11'">Ur-Namma, the shepherd and provider in Sumer and Akkad, loved by Enlil</l>
        <l n="12'">In his reign(?) that makes(?) (every)thing of Urim rejoice, you are the one who spends time there(?)</l>
        <l n="13'">Ur-Namma, king with an eternal name, your praise is sweet</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
