<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>CDLI Literary 000335, ex. 047</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ATF by atf2tei.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>
            CDLI
            <idno type="CDLI">P346204</idno>
          </title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" n="line" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pattern references a specific line.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="surface" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pattern references an inscribed surface on an object.</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div n="urn:cts:cdli:P346204.P346204.cdli-en" type="translation" xml:lang="en">
        <l n="1">In those distant days when fate was determined</l>
        <l n="2">The year (of?) abundance engendered by An/The year in which abundance and heaven (alike) were born(?)</l>
        <l n="3">When the people split (through) the earth like vegetation</l>
        <l n="4">The lord of the Abzu, king Enki</l>
        <l n="5">...(?) Enki, the lord who is to determine fate</l>
        <l n="6">Built his temple (with) the combination of(?) silver and lapis</l>
        <l n="7">The silver and lapis was something that (lit. of) glowing sunlight</l>
        <l n="8">He made(?) rosette/star decorations(?) in shrine Abzu</l>
        <l n="9">In the pure cultic space/crown(?) that was artfully crafted/furnished with stairs(?), coming out from the Abzu</l>
        <l n="10">... stood for/served lord Nudimmud</l>
        <l n="11">It was silver that he built the temple with</l>
        <l n="12">It was lapis that he made it colorful with</l>
        <l n="13">He adorned it(!?) greatly in gold</l>
        <l n="14">In Eridu he built the temple on the riverbank</l>
        <l n="15">Its brickwork speaks words and gives advice</l>
        <l n="16">Its reed layers within the brick bellowed like a bull</l>
        <l n="17">The temple of Enki is to shout nobly</l>
        <l n="18">The temple brought praise at(?) night for the king while presenting it sweetly/bending its knee (to him)(?)</l>
        <l n="19">For Enki, the vizier Isimud was speaking(?)</l>
        <l n="20">He stood in the temple and was speaking</l>
        <l n="21">He stood in the brickwork and was giving voice/explicating</l>
        <l n="22">House that was founded in silver and lapis, its foundation set in the Abzu</l>
        <l n="23">Cared for by the prince in the Abzu</l>
        <l n="24">Who accepted (its) supreme me(?) and aura in/from(?) the Tigris and Euphrates</l>
        <l n="25">Your door lock has no rival</l>
        <l n="26">Your bolt is a lion bearing an aura</l>
        <l n="27">Your roof beam is the bull of heaven, a pure cultic space/crown(?) that was artfully crafted/furnished with stairs(?)</l>
        <l n="28">(Your) reed mat sparkles in lapis/blue? towards the roof beams(?)</l>
        <l n="29">Your vault is a wild bull raising its horns</l>
        <l n="30">Your gate is a lion seizing a man</l>
        <l n="31">Your threshold is an ug creature going out towards a man</l>
        <l n="32">The Abzu, a pure place, fitting</l>
        <l n="1">E'engura temple, your king has set foot (there) for you</l>
        <l n="2">Enki, the king of the Abzu</l>
        <l n="3">He has set(?) carnelian along(?) your foundation</l>
        <l n="4">With incantations/noise(?) he has taken care of (your) lapis(?)</l>
        <l n="5">Temple whose pure wax design(?) has been inspected by Enki</l>
        <l n="6">A bull that is set on track for its master</l>
        <l n="7">Roaring on behalf of its aura(?) and advising (on behalf of) its dignity(?)</l>
        <l n="8">E'engura temple, (whose) pure reed fence has been hung/bound (together) by Enki</l>
        <l n="9">In your midst a supreme dais is founded</l>
        <l n="10">Your door jamb is the pure aškud bolt(?) of heaven/An</l>
        <l n="11">The lord of wisdom, king Enki</l>
        <l n="12">Nudimmud, the lord of Eridu</l>
        <l n="13">(In?) the “heart of the fallow deer,” into which no one can see</l>
        <l n="14">He has made(?) your abgal priest loosen (his) hair upon the back</l>
        <l n="15">When Enki loves Eridu(!?)</l>
        <l n="16">The midst of the E'engura temple is(?) filled with abundance</l>
        <l n="17">Abzu, the life of the land, beloved by Enki</l>
        <l n="18">Temple build on the edge, suitable for the elaborate cosmic powers</l>
        <l n="19">Eridu, your shade extends into the midst of the sea</l>
        <l n="20">Risen sea that has no rival</l>
        <l n="21">Supreme river possessing an aura and giving the land gooseflesh</l>
        <l n="22">E'engur temple, great flood(?) that touches the ground</l>
        <l n="23">Temple adjoining the deep water(!?), pirig creature in/of the inner Abzu</l>
        <l n="24">Supreme temple of Enki giving wisdom in the land</l>
        <l n="25">Your shout, like a risen river</l>
        <l n="26">Is singing for king Enki</l>
        <l n="27">Towards the holy temple he presents sweetly/bends (his?) knee (to it)(?)</l>
        <l n="28">The lyre, the algar instrument, the balag drum, and the tamborine/rattle</l>
        <l n="29">The harhar instrument, the sabitum instrument, and the “Mari instrument” that silences the temple(?)</l>
        <l n="30">(The ones with) a sweet voice and “releasing and growing&quot; lips</l>
        <l n="31">May they resound because of(?) their own hearts (i.e., their distinct sounds?)</l>
        <l n="32">The holy algar instrument of Enki has played itself for him</l>
        <l n="33">May the seven musicians sing/play(?)</l>
        <l n="1">The utterance of Enki, which is not to be changed</l>
        <l n="2">... is set towards its (proper) place</l>
        <l n="3">He is singing sweetly about(?) the brickwork of the E'engura temple</l>
        <l n="4">When/In that which he had built (the temple), in that he had built (the temple)</l>
        <l n="5">In that which Enki had raised in Eridu</l>
        <l n="6">Like/as a mountain range that is craftily knotted/equipped with stairs(?) it floats on the water</l>
        <l n="7">The reedbed dwells at its border(?)</l>
        <l n="8">In its verdant orchards that bear fruit</l>
        <l n="9">The bird sets foot/treads there(?)</l>
        <l n="10">The suhur carp plays(?) in the ulal plants(?)</l>
        <l n="11">The eštub carp flap their tails for him towards(!?) the tiny gizi reed grouth</l>
        <l n="12">When Enki rises, the fish rise as a wave</l>
        <l n="13">In the Abzu, he stands amid admiration</l>
        <l n="14">In the E'engura temple rejoicing ...</l>
        <l n="15">Like the sea, he can possess(?) an aura</l>
        <l n="16">He is a supreme river who can cast(?) a radiance</l>
        <l n="17">In the Euphrates river he can raise a furious southern wind</l>
        <l n="18">His boat pole (is) his serpent(?), Neraḫ</l>
        <l n="19">His oar(s) (are) his little kib birds</l>
        <l n="20">When Enki sails, the year is filled with abundance</l>
        <l n="21">The boat released itself and seized its own ropes(?)</l>
        <l n="22">After(?) he “fled” towards the temple of Eridu</l>
        <l n="23">In(?) the river ... was advising its king</l>
        <l n="24">(The one whose) voice (was) the voice of a calf, the voice of a sweet cow</l>
        <l n="25">Enki was slaughtering bulls and slaughtering sheep</l>
        <l n="26">He restored the ala drum that was not present to its (proper) place</l>
        <l n="27">He brought out the šem drum that was not present to its (proper) place</l>
        <l n="28">He set out alone towards Nibru</l>
        <l n="29">He was entering into the giguna terrace (of) shrine Nibru</l>
        <l n="30">Enki approached(!) the beer, he approached(!) the kurun liquor</l>
        <l n="31">He poured yellow(?) kurun liquor into a bronze (bowl?)</l>
        <l n="32">He filtered ulušin beer that was singular (in quality, frequency, or “he alone&quot;?)</l>
        <l n="33">He made kukurdu containers settle(?) in/with(?) the residue(?) of the very good/sweetened beer(?)</l>
        <l n="34">In its (the vessel's?) mouth he poured(?) date syrup ...</l>
        <l n="35">He “released&quot;(?) the residue by cooling it(?), (making it?) into “that which is mixed(!?)”</l>
        <l n="1">Enki, who was in shrine Nibru</l>
        <l n="2">For his father, Enlil, he was “making bread be eaten”</l>
        <l n="3">He seated ... An in what was the supreme place</l>
        <l n="4">For An, he made Enlil follow there</l>
        <l n="5">He seated Nintur in the “seat of honor” (lit. great(er) side)</l>
        <l n="6">He sat the Anuna gods in their “foundations&quot;(?)</l>
        <l n="7">They (lit. the people) were drinking, they were making themselves sweet(!?)with kurun liquor</l>
        <l n="8">They were rolling around (i.e., knocking over?) the bronze vessels (like/filled with?) apples(!?)</l>
        <l n="9">(They were making?) the bronze (bowls) have a contest with Uraš (i.e. the earth, by knocking them onto the ground)(?)</l>
        <l n="10">They were ... the bowl (shaped like?) the holy barge (i.e., the crescent moon?)(?)</l>
        <l n="11">After beer was drunk and kurun liquor was “enjoyed”</l>
        <l n="12">After they set foot away from the temple</l>
        <l n="13">Enlil ... rejoicing in Nibru</l>
        <l n="14">Enlil was speaking to the Anuna</l>
        <l n="15">Great gods who are present</l>
        <l n="16">Anuna, you who (assemble) properly in the Ubšu'ukken</l>
        <l n="17">My son built the temple, king Enki</l>
        <l n="18">He made Eridu distant(?) from the ground like a mountain range</l>
        <l n="19">It was a good place that he built the temple (in)</l>
        <l n="20">(In) Eridu, the pure place which no one is to enter</l>
        <l n="21">The temple built in silver and made colorful in lapis</l>
        <l n="22">The temple that (plays) the seven tigi drums properly and produces incantations/namšub prayers(?)</l>
        <l n="23">The pure and dignified(!?) šir songs that make the temple site sweet(?)</l>
        <l n="24">Shrine Abzu, the goodness of Enki, suitable for the elaborate me</l>
        <l n="25">It is the building of temple of silver of (i.e., in) Eridu</l>
        <l n="26">Enki, praise</l>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
